Finding Aid for Edwin Denby papers, 1845-1846, 1880-1927
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edwin Denby papers 1845-1846 1880-1927
Denby, Edwin, 1870-1929.
851116 Aa 2
United States Representative and Secretary of the Navy; collection includes correspondence, 1880-1927, concerning personal matters, business affairs, and political activities; letters to Mrs. Denby regarding Denby’s death; articles, speeches, notes and memoranda on various topics including the Teapot Dome Scandal, Panama Canal, relations with China, and the United States Navy; photostats of letters exchanged between Nathaniel Denby and George Bancroft, 1845-1846; and photographs.
2.4 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Received from Mrs. Marion Thurber Denby (Donor no. 1458 ) in 1941.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Edwin Denby was born on February 18, 1870 in Evansville, Indiana to Charles and Martha (Fitch) Denby. In 1885 he moved to China with his father, who had been appointed minister for the United States. Denby lived there for ten years, where he was employed in the Chinese imperial maritime customs service from1887 to 1894. Upon return to America, Denby enrolled in the Law School at the University of Michigan, receiving his L.L.B. in 1896.
Denby volunteered for service in the United States Navy during the Spanish-American War, serving as a gunner's mate aboard the Yosemite. He then returned to Detroit to practice law. Denby was elected as a Republican Representative to the Michigan legislature in 1903, and in 1905 was elected to represent Michigan's 1st District in the United States House of Representatives, serving from 1905 to 1911. After he lost the election in 1910 to Democrat Frank E. Doremus, Denby returned to his law practice in Detroit. When the United States entered World War I in 1917, he enlisted as a private in the United States Marine Corps. Denby retired in 1919 with the rank of Major (United States). He was then selected by President Warren G. Harding to be Secretary of the Navy, in which capacity he served from 1921 to 1924.
Denby is perhaps best known for his involvement in the Teapot Dome oil reserve scandal, which led to his resignation as Secretary of the Navy. In 1921, by executive order of the President, control of naval oil reserves at Teapot Dome, Wyo., and at Elk Hills, Calif., was transferred from the Navy Dept. to the Dept. of the Interior. In 1922, Albert B. Fall, U.S. Secretary of the Interior, leased, without competitive bidding, the Teapot Dome fields to Harry F. Sinclair, an oil operator, and the field at Elk Hills, Calif., to Edward L. Doheny. These transactions became (1922--23) the subject of a Senate investigation conducted by Sen. Thomas J. Walsh. Through the course of the investigation, it was found that Donehy had loaned or given large amounts of money to Fall, presumably in payment for the lucrative oil reserve leases. Fall was eventually indicted for conspiracy and for accepting bribes, and convicted of the latter charge (he was sentenced to a year in prison and fined $100,000).
Denby was not seriously charged, and was determined to have taken no significant part in the negotiations. A quote from The New York Tribune illustrates the public perception of Denby's involvement in the affair: "Stupidity is the high crime and misdemeanor which the Senate accuses Mr. Denby, and the only one." (Feb. 12, 1924). A senate vote on February 11, 1924 requested President Coolidge (Harding had died by this time) to dismiss Denby from his cabinet. Coolidge declined to dismiss Denby, who still insisted that the leases of the oil reserves were both legal and expedient. Nevertheless, Denby resigned his post on February 18, 1924, and in March returned once again to Detroit to practice law. He died there a few weeks before his 59th birthday.
Detroit's Denby High School is named in his honor, as is the Denby Center for Children and Family Services, which the Salvation Army opened in Detroit in 1930 to provide housing and treatment for abused and neglected children.
The Edwin Denby papers, dating from 1845-1846 and 1880-1929, are organized into five series: Correspondence, Articles and Speeches, Topical Files, Personal/Biographical, and Photographs. Denby's papers document his political career as United States Representative and Secretary of the Navy, and include relevant information on such topics as the United States Navy, the Panama Canal and the Teapot Dome Scandal.
Subjects:
Bancroft, George, 1800-1891.; China--History--Boxer Rebellion, 1899-1901.; Detroit Board of Commerce.; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Mason, John G.; Panama Canal (Panama); Petroleum industry and trade--United States.; United States. Navy.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Airplanes.; Airships.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Denby, Charles, 1830-1904.; Denby, Edwin, 1870-1929.; Dewey, George, 1837-1917.; Mount Clemens (Mich.)--Street-railroads.; Panama.; Ships.; Street-railroads--Michigan--Mount Clemens.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; China--History--1861-1912.
Contributors:
Cannon, Joseph Gurney, 1836-1926.; Clark, Emory W.; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948.; Denby, Nathaniel.; Griffin, Robert Stanislaus, 1857-1933.; Henderson, Charles B.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Kennedy, Joseph J.; Murphy, M. J.; Newberry, Truman Handy, 1864-1945.; Niblack, Albert Parker, 1859-1929.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1887-1944.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937.; Rose, Henry Martin, b. 1858.; Smith, Hal Horace, 1873-1944.; Sosnowksi, John B.; Tuttle, Arthur J., 1868-1944.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Wallace, Henry Cantwell, 1866-1924.; Walsh, Thomas James, 1859-1933.; Wilbur, Curtis Dwight, 1867-1954.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence 1845-1927
  The Correspondence series is organized chronologically, and contains not only correspondence by Edwin Denby but also photostats by Nathanial Denby written to the Secretary of the Navy in 1845-1847 and a copy of Graham N. Fitch and S.A. Douglas' correspondence.
  - 1880-1890 (Box 1)
  - 1891-1893 (Box 1)
  - 1894-1906 (Box 1)
  - 1907-January, 1908 (Box 1)
  - February-October 1908 (Box 1)
  - December 1908-1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911-1915 (Box 1)
  - 1917-1919 (Box 1)
  - 1921 (Box 1)
  - 1922 (Box 1)
  - 1923 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1924 (Box 1)
  - March 1924, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - April 1924, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - May 1924 (Box 1)
  - May-June 1924 (Box 1)
  - 1925 (Box 1)
  - January 1926 (Box 1)
  - February 1926 (Box 1)
  - March 1926, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - April 1926, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - May 1926 (Box 1)
  - June-November 1926 (Box 1)
  - 1927 (Box 1)
  - Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Other correspondence (not Edwin Denby)
    - Photostats of letters written by Nathaniel Denby, U.S. Navy Agent to George Bancroft, Sec. of Navy 1845-1846 (Box 1)
    - Photostats of letters written by Nathaniel Denby U.S. Navy Agent, to John G. Mason, Sec. of Navy 1847-1848 (Box 1)
    - Copy of Graham N. Fitch and S.A. Douglas correspondence January 21, 1859-January 24, 1859 (Box 1)
- Speeches and Articles
  The Articles and Speeches series contains articles and speeches written by Denby. The speeches included are organized chronologically where possible, and by topic in the case of undated speeches. Speeches given by Denby in his capacity as a United States Representative, as well as Secretary of the Navy, are included here.
  - Speeches
    - Detroit White Lead Works speech October 1904 (Box 1)
    - Republican Party speech November 3, 1904 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Board of Commerce speeches October 1912, February 1914, undated (Box 1)
    - Indian Village speech November 27, 1916 (Box 1)
    - "Eleven Popular Fallacies," February 1917 (Box 1)
    - "Men! It is Up to You!" An Address to Applicants for Enlistment in the United States Marine Corps September 1923 (Box 1)
    - Homecoming speech after resignation as Secretary of the Navy, Detroit MI March 13, 1924 (Box 1)
    - Undated Speeches
      - Campaign speech for 1904 House of Representatives election (Box 1)
      - Speeches on Chinese Issues (Box 1)
      - George Washington's birthday speech (Box 1)
      - House of Representatives speech on President Roosevelt and the House Appropriations Committee (Box 1)
      - Indiana speech (Box 1)
      - Introducing Senator Cannon from Illinois (Box 1)
      - Merchant Marine speeches (Box 1)
      - Panama Canal Treaty (Box 1)
      - South American Relations (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous political speeches (Box 1)
      - Handwritten speeches (Box 1)
  - Articles
    - "Chimes" article about Michigan football March 1921 (Box 1)
    - Letter to the Editor Detroit Free Press (Box 1)
    - Beaufort, South Carolina article written for The State, May, 1926 (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files include material collected and written by Denby on a variety of subjects: including relations with China, the Panama Canal, the Teapot Dome scandal, and his work as Secretary of the Navy.
  - China-related materials
    - Chinese Army -- General Summary April 11, 1907 (Box 1)
    - Memorandum on the bill providing for Extradition to and from China (Box 1)
    - "Some Considerations on Chinese Exclusion" by Edwin Denby (Box 1)
    - United States Court for China 1907 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous documents (Box 1)
      (including information about the U.S. Claims Commission in China and notes on the Boxer Indemnity Fund)
  - Court Marshall of Private William B. McStevens March 15, 1918 (Box 1)
    (Denby served as Counsel for the accused)
  - Detroit Board of Commerce, excerpts from minutes of Board of Directors meetings 1917, 1928, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Expropriation proceedings of Schuber lands at Corozal, N.Z. 1908 (Box 1)
  - League of Nations constitution (Box 1)
  - Naval Reserve Oil Bill of 1923 (Box 2)
  - Panama Canal
    - General information (Box 2)
    - Joint Commission Report, Administration Building May 20, 1907 (Box 2)
    - Verdict of the Joint Commission June 5, 1907 (Box 2)
    - Joint Commission, Statement and Brief of Attorneys for Claimants August 1, 1908 (Box 2)
  - Pension application of Elizabeth Farrand 1906 (Box 2)
  - Petitions for Denby to run for Senator 1917, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Secretary of the Navy materials
    - Articles on the Navy by Captain Frank Taylor Evans (Box 2)
    - "Economy Measures: Navy Department 1922" report by Edwin Denby (Box 2)
    - "Letters of a Retired Rear Admiral to his son in the Navy" by Rear Admiral A.P. Niblack, U.S.N. March 1923 (Box 2)
    - "The Psychology of the American Navy" by Edwin Denby (Box 2)
    - Memoranda 1921, 1923 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1921, 1923 undated (Box 2)
    - Extracts from the address of Curtis D. Wilbur, Secretary of the Navy, to the Republican Women of the District of Columbia May 5, 1924 (Box 2)
  - Teapot Dome Oil Reserve Scandal
    - Memoranda concerning the oil reserve scandal and Denby's resignation March 3-4, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Denby's response to Senator Walsh, regarding the article "What I Think of the Oil Scandal" by Theodore M. Knapper March 1924 (Box 2)
    - Homecoming speech at Detroit after resignation March 13, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Speech at Adrian April 19, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Speech at University of Michigan May 17, 1924 (Box 2)
- Personal/Biographical
  The Personal/Biographical files include information on Denby's time in the United States Marine Corps, about land owned by Denby in Oakland County, Michigan, biographical sketches and miscellaneous financial materials. Included in this series is a collection of jokes, poems and songs that may have been written by Denby or by friends. This series also contains funeral and memorial materials from the time of Denby's death, including condolence letters sent to Mrs. Denby (which are organized alphabetically by the last name of the sender) as well as materials from Denby's actual funeral.
  - Blueprints of Drayton Woods, Oakland County, Mich. (Box 2)
    (owned by Edwin Denby and John E. Baker)
  - Chinese New Year's card 1890 (Box 2)
  - Description of Oakland County land owned by Denby (Box 2)
  - Diplomas and Certificates of Membership (Box 2)
  - "Edwin Denby", biographical sketch by M. Hubert O'Brien (Box 2)
  - Financial statements, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Fitch family tree (Box 2)
    (Denby's mother's family tree)
  - Funeral and memorial materials
    - Notes sent to Mrs. Denby upon the death of her husband, A-Z and last name unknown, 24 folders (Box 2)
    - Letter to Gov. Green, which concerns a proposed memorial to Denby May 15, 1929 (Box 2)
    - Funeral materials, including text of sermon and order of service February 11, 1929 (Box 2)
    - Cards, attached to flowers sent at the time of Denby's death, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Thank you letters written by Mrs. Denby after her husband's death (Box 2)
    - Thank you letters written to Mrs. Denby after her husband's death (Box 2)
    - Resolutions on the Death of Edwin Denby, Gristmill Club and Banker's Trust Company of Detroit (Box 2)
  - "The Future in the Air", by George M. Battey, Jr., written for the christening of the Shenandoah by Mrs. Denby, October 10, 1923 (Box 2)
  - History of Charles Fort, Parris Island, South Carolina (Box 2)
  - Marine Corps materials
    - Blueprint; Billeting area, Depot Division First Corps A.E.F., France (Box 2)
    - Health record of Denby when a Captain in the U.S. Marine Corps 1918 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Marine Corps documents (Box 2)
  - Notebook containing drafts for articles and speeches (Box 2)
  - Notes by Thomas Spencer Jerome to Edwin Denby (Box 2)
    (including Jerome's writings on various topics)
  - Poems, jokes and songs undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (includes membership cards, receipts, cancelled checks, tax materials and personal cards)
  - Copy of "A Message of Friendship," delivered to E. Denby March 13, 1917 by the Board of Directors of the Detroit Board of Commerce (Folder 1)
  - Menu of complimentary dinner to Denby April 30, 1921 (Folder 1)
  - Resolutions of commendation and thanks to Denby by the Post Office Clerks, Branch 16, U.N.A.P.O.C (Folder 1)
  - Map of Naval Reserve No. 3 (Wyoming), showing contours on second sand and oil and gas development of the Mamouth Oil Company, as of July 1, 1923 (Folder 1)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series contains a variety of images of Denby, from his time at the University of Michigan, in the Navy in the Spanish American War, and his later career as a politician and cabinet member. Also included are images of China and Panama, images of United States Navy ships and planes, and unidentified portraits.
  - China (Box 3)
  - China-People (Box 3)
  - Mount Clemens, Michigan Interurban (Box 3)
  - Navy-Aviation (Box 3)
  - Navy-Ships (Box 3)
  - Panama (Box 3)
  - People-Unidentified (Box 3)
  - Portraits (Box 3)
  - Charles Denby (Box 3)
    (includes portrait with George Dewey)
  - Edwin Denby (Box 3)
  - Fitch family (Box 3)
  - Ships-Great Lakes (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 3)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Cannon, Joseph Gurney, 1836-1926.
Oct. 4, 1910
Clark, Emory W.
March 7, 1924
Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933.
Feb. 18, 1924, April 3, 1926
Couzens, James 1872-1936.
Jan. 18, 1908, Jan. 21, 1908, April 17, 1908, March 8, 1924, May 1, 1924
Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948.
March 4, 1921, March 5, 1921, June 7, 1926, Feb. 8, 1929, Feb. 26, 1929
Griffin, Robert Stanislaus, 1857-1933.
Sept. 22, 1921
Henderson, Charles B.
March 10, 1921
Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.
Jan. 5, 1924
Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.
April 3, 1924
Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.
March 9, 1924
Kennedy, Joseph J.
1921-1926
Murphy, M. J.
March 15, 1924
Newberry, Truman Handy, 1864-1945.
March 10, 1924
Niblack, Albert Parker, 1859-1929.
Feb. 19, 1921
Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860
March 12, 1924, April 10, 1926, Nov. 29, 1926, Jan. 2, 1927
Roosevelt, Theodore, 1887-1944.
Aug.1, 1923, April 10, 1924
Rose, Henry Martin, b. 1858.
Mar. 10, 1924, Mar. 31, 1924, Apr. 3, 1924, Apr. 29, 1924, Mar. 27, 1926
Smith, Hal Horace, 1873-1944.
Apr. 10, 1924, Apr. 11, 1924, May 1, 1924
Sosnowksi, John B.
Mar. 26, 1926
Tuttle, Arthur J., 1868-1944.
Mar. 7, 1924
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Apr. 3, 1924
Wallace, Henry Cantwell, 1866-1924.
Mar. 31, 1924
Walsh, Thomas James, 1859-1933.
Mar. 10, 1921
Wilbur, Curtis Dwight, 1867-1954.
June 7, 1926, Feb. 8, 1929, Feb. 26, 1929